Planned Parenthood Federation of America Records (PPFA II): SERIES I. Chronological Files, 1964-80
Sophia Smith Collection
Planned Parenthood Federation of America Records (PPFA II): SERIES I. Chronological Files
1964-80
Planned Parenthood Federation of America
371a_s1
29.25 linear feet
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This series consists primarily of carbon copies of outgoing correspondence, the bulk of which is from the national office, 1960s-70s. The authors of this correspondence include PPFA staffers Alan Bloebaum, Hans Blaise, Eve Paul, Alan Guttmacher, John C. Robbins, Fred Jaffe, and Jerim Klapper. This Series forms part of the PPFA II Records
This Series forms part of the PPFA II Records
This series consists primarily of carbon copies of outgoing correspondence, the bulk of which is from thenational office, 1960s-70s. It is arranged alphabetically by the last name of the author of the letter. Each individual's correspondence is arranged in reverse chronological order. The authors of this correspondence include many significant PPFA staffers, including Alan Bloebaum, Hans Blaise, Eve Paul, Alan Guttmacher, John C. Robbins, Fred Jaffe, and Jerim Klapper. Researchers may find it useful to consult administrative files first (SERIES II. CLASSIFIED), determine pertinent departments and staffers, and then consult the Chronological Files. See appendix for list of selected PPFA staff and their positions.
NOTE: To view the series descriptions and contents lists, click on the series links below. Some files are quite large and may take several minutes to load, depending on your internet connection.
This collection is organized into ten series:
I. Chronological Files
II. Classified Files
Part 1
Part 2
III. Publications
IV. Subject Files
V. Affiliates
Part 1
Part 2
VI. Regions
VII. Minutes
VIII. Foreign
IX. Guttmacher
[SERIES X. Restricted]
PPFA has closed records created January 1, 1985 or later, with the exception of many published materials which are open to research. All records having to do with clinic defense and security are closed. PPFA has closed a small section of files in box 206 for fifty years. Researchers may request access to restricted materials from PPFA.
The Margaret Sanger Papers Microfilm Edition: Smith College Collection Series, edited by Esther Katz, et al., University Publications of America, 1995
Periodic additions to the collection are expected.
PPFA deposited these records in 1988. Various departments have since sent miscellaneous additions.
Best, Winfield; Guttmacher, Alan Frank, 1898-; McCormick, Katherine Dexter, 1876-1967; Rose, D. Kenneth; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966; Wattleton, Faye; Alan Guttmacher Institute--History; American Birth Control League--History; Abortion--Law and legislation-United States--History--Sources; Abortion services--History--Sources; Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau (New York, N.Y.)--History; Birth Control Federation of America--History; International Planned Parenthood Federation--History; Planned Parenthood Federation of America--History; Planned Parenthood-World Population (U.S.)--History; Birth control clinics--United States--History--Sources; Birth control--History--20th century--Sources; Birth control--Developing countries--History--20th century--Sources; Contraceptives--Research--History; Hygiene, Sexual--History--20th century; Human reproduction--Political aspects; Population policy--History--20th century; Reproductive health--Statistics; Sex instruction--History; Women--Health and hygiene--United States--20th century; Women's health services--United States--20th century
This Series forms part of the PPFA II Records
See also the PPFA I Records.
Related material can be found in the Margaret Sanger Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, and at the Library of Congess.
- SERIES I. CHRONOLOGICAL
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1980-75 (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
    - 1974-71 (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
  - Allen, Gerald 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Anderson, Richard 1970-69 (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
  - Andreen, Mrs. John
    - 1972-74 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1975-80 (Box 1)
  - Atlee, Elinor 1972-69 (Box 1, Folder 19-22)
  - Bacon, S. Allen 1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Baldwin, Barbara 1979-77 (Box 1, Folder 24-27)
  - Nestor, R. Barry 1970 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Baum, Mrs. Morton J. 1966-67 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Beach, George R. 1970-71 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Beasley, Joseph D. 1969-71 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bedient, Vanessa 1967-68 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Bernheim, Doris
    - 1973-69 (Box 1, Folder 33-48)
    - 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bernsohn, Carita 1969-66 (Box 2, Folder 2-5)
  - Win Best Chron Files, [Out] (Box 2)
  - Blair, Beatrice 1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Blaise, Hans 1977-76 (Box 2, Folder 7-13)
  - Bloebaum, Alan P.
    - 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
    - 1974-72 (Box 2, Folder 17-28)
    - 1971-69 (Box 3, Folder 1-12)
  - Bloebaum, Alan P., Folders 1964-1968, [See Box 23, pp. 54-5] (Box 3)
  - Bohlman, Robert 1968-70 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Bridges, Leon 1970 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Brightman, Clare
    - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 1974-66 (Box 3, Folder 16-41)
  - Brown, Clinton H. 1970 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Browning, Robert H. 1967 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Buckner, Nancy
    - 1974 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - 1975 (Box 3)
  - Calabi, Paul F. 1967-68 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Campbell, Jan, formerly Schinning 1972-74 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Canfield, Cass
    - 1974-65 (Box 3, Folder 47-48)
    - 1964 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Cardenas, Daniel 1972-70 (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
  - Carlson, Robert J. 1970-68 (Box 4, Folder 7-14)
  - Chapman, Ruth H. (Mrs. Carleton B.) 1970-71 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Churchill, Marion 1979 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Clifford, Mrs. Henry H. 1970-65 (Box 4, Folder 17-19)
  - Corbin, Jill A. 1979 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Coleman, Randall C. 1969-67 (Box 4, Folder 21-27)
  - Cope, Judith 1970 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Cordellos, Betty 1971-70 (Box 4, Folder 29-31)
  - Cowles, Wylda B. 1966-65 (Box 4, Folder 32-33)
  - Crawford, Robert D. 1970-68 (Box 4, Folder 34-40)
  - Davies, Sara T. 1969-64 (Box 4, Folder 41-45)
  - Davis, Phyliss 1977-76 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Davis, Roger E. 1970-71 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Day, Richard Dr. 1966-65 (Box 4, Folder 48-56)
  - Dean, Charles R., PhD. 1969-67 (Box 4, Folder 57-60)
  - Diaz, Andrew W. 1978-76 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - Dick, Rollin M.
    - 1972-74 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1975 (Box 5)
    - 1972 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Dickler, Susan 1973-71 (Box 5, Folder 8-12)
  - Dieckman, Emil W. 1969-68 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Diener, Mrs. Walter
    - 1967-74 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - 1975-78 (Box 5)
  - Dornan, David 1976-75 (Box 5, Folder 15-17)
  - Driscoll, Joan K., (formerly Kraken) 1980-77 (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
  - Dryfoos, Joy 1972-68 (Box 5, Folder 20-21)
  - Du Bois, Dorothy 1974-68 (Box 5, Folder 22-46)
  - Duncan, Nancy Y. 1979 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Escedy, Marlee M. 1971-67 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Edelmann, Norah 1970 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Elliot, Robin A. 1971-69 (Box 6, Folder 3-5)
  - Elrod, Jerry 1973-72 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - Epstein, Beatrice, (formerly Mrs. Harper Sibley -see for previous years) 1972 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Evants, John E. 1971-70 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
  - Ewenstein, Edith 1974-66 (Box 6, Folder 11-25)
  - Fansler, John B. 1966-63 (Box 6, Folder 26-27)
  - Fennessy, Richard 1970-68 (Box 6, Folder 28-33)
  - Ferguson, Richard A. 1973-70 (Box 6, Folder 34-37)
  - Finks, Willogene
    - 1974 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - 1975 (Box 6)
  - Fisher, Donald 1970-69 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Fleischman, Norman 1967-66 (Box 6, Folder 40-44)
  - Foreman, Carol T. 1970 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Freedheim, Mrs. E.H. 1969-65 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Freeman, Emily 1968 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Garwood, Miriam, 1/64-3/73, [Out] (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Gatov, Mrs. Albert 1970-68 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Gaye, Winston
    - 1977-76 (Box 6, Folder 50-55)
    - 1976-75 (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
    - 1974 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Gilbert, William 1978 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Giles, Alfred 1979-77 (Box 7, Folder 9-15)
  - Gillespie, Mrs. G.E. 1974-65 (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
  - Gilman, Ted 1967 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Gilpatric, Marguerite 1971-70 (Box 7, Folder 19-20)
  - Gold, Esther G. 1972-70 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Gooch, Nancy 1974-72 (Box 7, Folder 22-29)
  - [Gray, Naomi, 1/64-1969], [Out] (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Gorman, Joseph, J. 1968-66 (Box 7, Folder 31-33)
  - Green, Larkin 1968 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Gregory, Mrs. William D. 1973-70 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Grymes, Sandra 1980-76 (Box 7, Folder 36-43)
  - Guttmacher, Alan F.
    - 1973-70 (Box 7, Folder 44-47)
    - 1970-64 (folder 19 [?] includes "8 Pictures"?) (Box 8, Folder 1-25)
  - Guy, Marlene 1980-79 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Hall, Leila V. 1974-70 (Box 8, Folder 27-29)
  - Hall, L. Priscilla 1979 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Hare, Claire
    - 1976-75 (Box 8, Folder 31-33)
    - 1974-72 (Box 8, Folder 34-35)
  - Harrod, Elizabeth 1968-69 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Hazzard, Virginia 1970-69 (Box 8, Folder 37-38)
  - Hayes, Bonnie 1973 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - [Hamilton, Madrid, 9/64-1/66], [Out] (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Hedstrom, Philip 1974-73 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Hensley, Charles C. 1968-67 (Box 8, Folder 42-44)
  - Herron, Charles 1974-71 (Box 8, Folder 45-50)
  - Herz, Herbert 1971-69 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - Hickie, Jane 1971-70 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Holland, Jerome H. 1970-69 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Hollins, B.T., M.D. 1978-77 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Hougan, Lee R. 1970-69 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Horowitz, Blanche 1972-64 (Box 9, Folder 3-8)
  - Hyacinthe, Laurent 1976 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Jackson, Elsie 1967-64 (Box 9, Folder 10-17)
  - Jaffe, Frederick S. 1970-64 (Box 9, Folder 18-37)
  - Johnson, Gina
    - 1971-70 (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - 1977 (Box 9)
  - Johnson, Jane 1979 (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - Johnson, Paulette
    - 1978-76 (Box 9, Folder 40-42)
    - 1974 (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - 1975 (Box 9)
  - Kassel, Charlotte 1970 (Box 9, Folder 44)
  - Kelly, Martin 1969-66 (Box 9, Folder 45-46)
  - Kimball, Richard H. 1966 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Klapper, Jerim 1971-69 (Box 10, Folder 2-10)
  - Klassel, Dara 1979 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Knipe, Kathleen 1972 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Kohler, James 1976 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - [McKafee, R., from Mar. 22-], [Out] (Box 10)
  - Kohler, James S. 1975 (Box 10, Folder 14-16)
  - Krakes, Joan M. 1977 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Kraus, Joan 1974-72 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Kraus, Mrs. Laurence 1971-68 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Krosky, Robert 1970-68 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Landman, Lynn C. 1970-69 (Box 10, Folder 21-26)
  - Langmyhr, Geo., M.D. 1972-66 (Box 10, Folder 27-32)
  - Levenson, Eleanor 1973-72 (Box 10, Folder 33-34)
  - Levine, Ethel 1970 (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Lavine, Karen 1979 (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Lincoln, Richard 1969-66 (Box 10, Folder 37-41)
  - Lindsay, Thomas B. 1976 (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - Lindsay, George N. 1968-66 (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - Livengood, Margaret 1970-69 (Box 10, Folder 44-45)
  - Louderbough, Olga
    - 1974-72 (Box 10, Folder 46)
    - 1976-75 (Box 10)
  - Mc Cartney, William 1969-68 (Box 10, Folder 47)
  - Mc Intyre, Henry L. 1969 (Box 10, Folder 48)
  - Mc Neil, Betty 1969-68 (Box 10, Folder 49)
  - Mallender, Fred 1978-77 (Box 10, Folder 50)
  - Manisoff, Miriam
    - 1969-68 (Box 10, Folder 51)
    - 1967-65 (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
  - Mapes, Gwen E. 1968 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Marren, James
    - 1973 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - 1976-75 (Box 11)
    - 1971-70 (Box 11, Folder 7-10)
  - Marshall, Mrs. J 1979-75 (Box 11, Folder 11-13)
  - Martin, Ruth M. 1970-66 (Box 11, Folder 14-15)
  - Mayers, Francis X. 1970 (Box 11, Folder 16-17)
  - Merritt, Claudine 1978-75 (Box 11, Folder 18-25)
  - Meyer, Leni Smith 1978-76 (Box 11, Folder 26-29)
  - [Millstone, Dorothy, 4/64-9/65], [Out] (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Mitchell, Richard 1965 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Mondy, Lewis W. 1974-71 (Box 11, Folder 32-43)
  - Nestor, R. Barry 1970 (Box 11, Folder 44)
  - Noyes, Mrs. Charles 1976-75 (Box 11, Folder 45)
  - O'Brien, Eleanor 1974-67 (Box 11, Folder 46)
  - Palmer, Earl 1973-74 (Box 11, Folder 47-48)
  - Parker, David 1970-69 (Box 11, Folder 49)
  - Patterson, Charles A. 1969-68 (Box 11, Folder 50-52)
  - Paul, Eve
    - 1979 (Box 11, Folder 53-54)
    - 1979-78 (Box 12, Folder 1-5)
  - Pellegrom, Daniel 1970-69 (Box 12, Folder 6-8)
  - Penunuri, Ralph G. 1970 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Perez, Alfredo J. 1970-68 (Box 12, Folder 10-15)
  - Perkin, Dr. G.W. 1966-64 (Box 12, Folder 16-24)
  - Phelps, Mrs. Stowe C. 1965-62 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Polgar, Steven Dr. 1967-64 (Box 12, Folder 26-37)
  - Potts, Leah 1971 (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - Potter, James F. 1974-72 (Box 12, Folder 39)
  - Price, Ralph D.L.
    - 1974-72 (Box 12, Folder 40-45)
    - 1972-66 (Box 13, Folder 1-24)
  - Prinz, Lucie 1967 (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - Pross, Albert E. 1974-71 (Box 13, Folder 26-31)
  - Randall, Sue 1969-68 (Box 13, Folder 32)
  - Redfern, Ronald 1974-73 (Box 13, Folder 33-34)
  - Richardson, Mary E.
    - 1974-72 (Box 13, Folder 35-37)
    - 1975 (Box 13, Folder 38)
  - Richardson, Russell
    - 1970 (Box 13, Folder 39)
    - 1976-75 (Box 13)
    - 1970-69 (Box 13, Folder 40-44)
    - 1969-64 (Box 14, Folder 1-19)
  - Rickin, Sheila 1973-71 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Riggs, Sonya W. 1976-75 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Rives, Sharon K. 1972-71 (Box 14, Folder 22-27)
  - Roach, Deborah
    - 1975 (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - 1973 (Box 14, Folder 29-31)
  - Robbins, Garald 1974-70 (Box 14, Folder 32-41)
  - Robbins, John C.
    - 1975 (Box 14, Folder 42-43)
    - 1974 (Box 14, Folder 44)
    - 1974 (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
    - [March, 1970 - Oct., 1973Out], See Boxes 23 and 24 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Robinson, Wylda, C. 1970-68 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Roderick, James T. 1980-76 (Box 15, Folder 6-15)
  - Rodman, Jules 1971-70 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Rogers, Walter 1970 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Romberg, Mrs. Marcia 1969-66 (Box 15, Folder 18-20)
  - Rosoff, Jeannie I. 1974-64 (Box 15, Folder 21-33)
  - Salberg, Murray 1970-69 (Box 15, Folder 34-37)
  - Scanlan, John S. 1971-69 (Box 15, Folder 38-44)
  - Scott. Mrs. Katherine N. 1967 (Box 15, Folder 45)
  - Selwyn, Jane
    - 1973 (Box 15, Folder 46)
    - 1972 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - Shalit, Sheldon 1970-68 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Sibley, Mrs. Harper 1970-67 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Silver, Morton A. 1971-68 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Smith, John Palmer 1971-70 (Box 16, Folder 6-9)
  - Snyder, Eleanor M. 1972-68 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Soroka, Margery 1970-66 (Box 16, Folder 11-15)
  - Speckman, Carl E. 1969-65 (Box 16, Folder 16-28)
  - Stanford, Helen
    - 1973-67 (Box 16, Folder 29-51)
    - 1967-65 (Box 17, Folder 1-6)
  - Stein, Francine
    - 1979-75 (Box 17, Folder 7-17)
    - 1974-68 (Box 17, Folder 18-32)
  - Stewart, Douglas 1970-67 (Box 17, Folder 33-37)
  - Still, Peggie 1965-64 (Box 17, Folder 38-41)
  - Stott, Mrs. Louis L. 1967-66 (Box 17, Folder 42)
  - Strauss, Donald B. 1968-64 (Box 17, Folder 43-44)
  - Strutz, Eileen
    - 1972-70 (Box 17, Folder 45-49)
    - 1969-68 (Box 18, Folder 1-4)
  - Stuart, Martha 1968-66 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Sussman, Mrs. Norton 1973-69 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Suthers, Derwent
    - 1979-75 (Box 18, Folder 7-20)
    - 1974-69 (Box 18, Folder 21-43)
  - Swall, John E.
    - 1974-73 (Box 18, Folder 44-49)
    - 1973-70 (Box 19, Folder 1-12)
  - Sweezy, Alan 1974-69 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Tangal, Peter 1974-70 (Box 19, Folder 14-15)
  - Taylor, Samuel 1970-68 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Thomas, Jesse L. 1978 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Tiffany, Terrence 1974-70 (Box 19, Folder 18-33)
  - Todd, Paul H.
    - 1969-68 (Box 19, Folder 34-42)
    - 1967 (Box 20, Folder 1-3)
  - Toscano, Fausto 1970-69 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Trobe, Adele S. 1969-67 (Box 20, Folder 5-12)
  - Tubbs, Ann
    - 1978 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - 1971 (Box 20)
  - Tucker, Gretchen
    - 1975 (Box 20, Folder 15-18)
    - 1974-73 (Box 20, Folder 19-24)
  - Varky, George 1969-67 (Box 20, Folder 25-30)
  - Van Gorder, David 1977 (Box 20, Folder 31)
  - Vineyard, Mrs. G. 1973-68 (Box 20, Folder 32-36)
  - Webb, Calvin 1970-69 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Webber, Robert
    - 1978-75 (Box 21, Folder 2-14)
    - 1974-72 (Box 21, Folder 15-26)
    - 1971 (Box 22, Folder 1-3)
  - Weinberg, David 1970-69 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Welsh, Mrs. George
    - 1974-73 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - 1975 (Box 22)
  - Whitten, Mrs. Chas. F. 1970-68 (Box 22, Folder 6-7)
  - Whitmore, George D. 1971-70 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Williams, Phyllis 1978 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Williams, Fred 1971-70 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Willis, William J.
    - 3/1/71-1974 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - 1975 (Box 22)
    - 1970-69 (Box 22, Folder 12-15)
  - Wilson, Beryl R.
    - 1973 (Box 22, Folder 16)
    - 1976-75 (Box 22, Folder 17-22)
    - 1974 (Box 22, Folder 23-26)
  - Winders, George J. 1971-67 (Box 22, Folder 27-39)
  - Wood, Thomas 1974-73 (Box 22, Folder 40)
  - Young, Arthur L. 1971-70 (Box 22, Folder 41-44)
  - Zukowski, Charles F. 1970 (Box 22, Folder 45)
  - Bloebaum, Alan P. 1968-64 (Box 23, Folder 1-33)
  - Robbins, John C.
    - 1973-72 (Box 23, Folder 34-38)
    - 1973-70 (Box 24, Folder 1-11)
  - Personal Chron. File 1968 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - "Public Affairs," 1979 (Box 24, Folder 13)